fabulous right so our next presentation
is going to be from Steven ball who if
you've seen his profile picture on the
website he may be slightly scared off
I'm sure he's lovely um he's going to be
talking about exploring Vector search at
scale and Steven is a developer Advocate
at zillis um and he's worked as a ml
engineer at Walt and our data scientists
at
Bravo and he's the a founding member of
the ml Ops community in Berlin uh
there's a group they do meetups things
like this meetups iens workshops lot of
workshops and all kinds of lovely
machine learning things and uh as
previously made he enjoys boxing and
surfing and uh maybe not at the same
time I'm trying but you're trying
surfing is hard enough already okay so
please put your hands together for
thank you very
much thank you very much for the
introduction yeah just to bounce back on
what you just said uh so I run the ml
Community chapter in Berlin uh and to
bounce back to the talk of before we're
doing an event with girls in Tech aaria
now end of November uh so if you know
some people that will be interested in
joining the workshop uh either you can
come to me we can come to directly as
well she's also part of it uh so yes all
also second thing uh I'm not a woman but
I've never been as stressed as I am
today as giving a talk because I've been
in the search industry for seven months
and before that I was in the mofs
industry for years um so yes but uh
that's enough about me I'm going to talk
start uh with a bit of a story we're
going to go on a bit of a
journey hopefully you can relate to the
first talk that we heard today uh which
is very funnily relate a lot to what I'm
going to talk today about so my slides
want to change
maybe maybe
not maybe not my slice don't change it's
fine uh it's a bit annoying you know but
uh I can just improve
um and let's go
no we're going to try
again it's the part of the demo effect
you know but in fact I also have live
demo after so I hope it will work
perfect it works so imagine uh you are
an AI developer kind of you start you
know the happy Beginnings you're like
working on your laptop everything works
H you're like you know you have this
genius idea of doing an AI product maybe
you're going to apply to your IC you
know as we've seen in the past couple of
days you just need to foro and then you
get funding so you use your favorite
text tack of 2024 car and clode you know
you don't need really to write codes
you're just going to ask uh for them to
write the code for you directly you have
your app you're pretty happy um and then
everything's
beautiful you have some instrict data
that's not a problem we spammed you
Vector databases we spammed you in 2023
2024 for how to use a vector database so
hopefully you have an idea and then you
know you're going to use Docker you're
going to pull any Vector database um and
then you're going to use it you start it
you're going to use some embedding
models and then you're going to store
your vectors directly you're happy
everything works well get some tractions
for your app um and then yes but then
you know you have more and more data
coming you start to have some pains you
know some Growing Pains as well uh maybe
if you're even fancy you're going to use
some multimodal data so you know what
used to take I don't know less than 10
milliseconds for your search now taking
500 milliseconds you know even longer as
well your index which used to be you
know updated very very quickly now it's
going to take you know like some hours
you know instead of like doing it live
you're doing it at night and every
morning you pray that it actually worked
if you do it daily you might do it
weekly but then you know your users is
going to be annoyed uh your frustration
Rises you know your product which used
to be so cool your AI product you know
uh then now like the search quality is
not good
enough so we're going to start again uh
basically now you're going to start with
a blank Enver you know you learned that
maybe just adding data to a v database
won't work
um to like a crazy scale so how do you
how do you going to solve that you know
first let's have a look at you know that
they different type of index I won't
explain the indexes directly uh because
most of you are very likely more
familiar than me about all the indexes
uh but let's say that you know you have
hash based and tree based you won't use
those um those are not really useful in
oural use case but then you have two
most important one which are the graph
based and inverted files you know agent
W that you probably heard I don't know
about thousand times last year um and
then you have the Mana which is disn is
the fancy name um but then also you know
you're going to look at inverted file um
and maybe you're going to go for
those then you have an idea of you know
which index work how they work a bit
more but then you kind of want to
balance you know like the speed and
accuracy uh for your search so you have
a look at compression you know like are
you going to go for flat or are you
going to go for something at is qu High
you know you have like different
algorithms um because you know you're oh
yeah actually I want a lot of data I
have lot of data but you know like if
you search it uh and if you don't
quantize it maybe sometime it's going to
be slow so then you just you know have a
look think about you know which one you
to go
for and the journey continues continue
you know like now you have a better idea
of what like the index you know you
don't think um like you know as naively
as before or you would just go for like
the default one
then you know like so back there a
software engineer um and you know we
always said that you know if you go
distributed you have more problems than
you actually solve so I'm actually going
to decide to go distributed because I
like to suffer a bit uh but basically
you're going to have a dilemma now so
you've optimized your index so you're
happy you've chosen the right data
structure so you're also quite happy and
then you've also like you know how to
look at like different compression
techniques so you have a better idea of
what's Happening
but you still have the problem you know
like more data in one instance is just
like not enough so it's like how do you
do that then how do you solve that so
yeah we're go distributed and if you
remember like the talk of this morning
basically um that's kind of what they
did you know then there was also a
mention of sharding so are you going to
do Shing are you going to go divide and
conquer so you're like you know you're
going to brainstorm some different
ideas and maybe you go random Shing you
know like then you know like it's very
simple but then you have an even
distribution maybe hash B Shing you know
more even distribution but then might be
tricky with
update and then semantic sharting you
know you might group some similar
vectors together um and then maybe
you're going to be happy with
that but you know it's only that then
you're also thinking oh you look at your
data and maybe I don't know you're
indexing you want to do it for fun
you're indexing Wikipedia uh because
you've seen an articles you know it's
like I don't know it's like 350 Millions
uh if I remember coh numbers and you
realize that you know maybe you can
partition language so you look at your
data and you're like actually that's
really good so sketch out of plan so you
have the data that is coming you know
you root it to like appropriate
partitions then you query um you the
queries first you know to determine the
languages and then the search executed
only on the relevant partition so you
don't do it everywhere and you like save
allot of time
so that way yeah you reduce a SE space
so then you have faster results and then
you know you're pretty happy you have
Shing you have poti
Shing but then what about you know your
reading as well so you're going to scale
horizontally you're going to have
replicas you have you know you have each
out of multiple replicas and then the
request are also load
balanced and the right operations are
also
synchronized and you know that's way
you're like yeah no I can read lot of
data you know at the same time
everything's happen
there has another problem which is this
one uh which is the cap theorem which
you are likely very familiar with but
you know you can't have consistency
availability and partition tolerance at
the same time so then you have a look
you decide which one to go for you you
read on the internet that you know you
can't have all of
them but then wa it's not over what
about real time now you know you users
now we want it now we always want I'm
addicted to like real time things so I I
really hate waiting so then yeah you I
want it knife I have your cool product
so then you may be going to use like
writer head logs maybe some two-tier
systems you know maybe like the fresh
data is sted somewhere and then your
historical data is St somewhere else
what about the index you know are going
to build an incremental
indexing so those are like the things
you have to think about if you want to
go real
time and monitoring you know like uh
back in my old days not that old but you
know back in the past
uh I work in the mlof world and data
scientists usually love to put models in
production never think about monitoring
um so yeah keep that in mind as well uh
in that case so you know like have check
the query latency the index update times
resource
utilizations um and different things
then maybe you implement some automated
processes you know to rebalance your
shards you add or you remove replicas
and maybe you want to perform running
updates you
know then you go have a look do you want
to host it somewhere or not you know
like maybe you're going to go on cloud
or maybe you continue on your own
info so yeah it's basically an never
ending Journey uh I think from what I
gathered from The Talk this morning it
can secure you a job at delivery hero um
if you want to redo everything basically
uh but maybe you don't want that uh
because you know like you always have to
basically keep up with what's happening
like you know like maybe there's a new
index algorithm that is coming maybe you
have some optimization for like GP
Factor search or some C CPU specific
ones and different things like that so
yeah if you did that congratulations you
just built milis um that's basically
what we do uh and yeah that's what I'm
going to talk about now uh that's the
architecture we have no worries I won't
bore you with like too much details uh
but that's a fully distributed
architecture so we have you know as I
said during the talk we have a load
balancer we're happy then we balance
that we have like different Services
running so the coordinator services are
here they're just here to tell you where
to go basically then we have log Brokers
so it's either CFA or PSAR so you know
we have access as well to the real time
data then we have some nodes which are
in the communities World which are
basically pods uh those ones are very
stupid you know they just get some data
from point A to point B and then we
store everything in S3 so that's very
similar to what I heard this morning uh
so very good job on this one uh we're
going on the same route so that's cool
uh but yes that's basically it and I'm
going to touch more about how we
actually can do it like at billion scale
um and the way we do it um so we use
minio to like store vectors and indexes
so everything you know is like fully
stateless for
us uh then we have KFAN for for you know
data insertion and World Time data
updates then unon like the usual
Prometheus and grafana and then we have
um CDs Direct ly as when I run it
directly on
kuber and a bit more into the details so
we have shards by default so like we can
boost like you know the ingestion rate
and then in milis we have what is called
a segment which is a single unit of data
and a segment is smaller than a
partition which is smaller than a
connection and when you push some data
what we have we have two kinds of
segments so we have the growing segment
which is the one you know handling real
time update and on this one we just
build a bridge for index so you can
query it directly and then we have seal
segments which are the one that are
immutable you know and then on this one
you build an index and then you do the
search so again very similar to what
they built this morning so I hope I
pretty sure they on the right Road
here so yes fully distributed
architecture basically some nodes to go
into it so the query node is only here
you know subscrib to the lock broker for
real time quering and it's also the one
that is converting new data into the
growing segment so you know the realtime
data that you have that's what allows
you to then query directly then he also
has access to the seal segments so those
ones are the old one they are like on
the object storage and that's where you
build the index on top of also allows
you to do like hybrid search uh if you
fcy that the other one data node you
know it's subscribed to the log broker
again but this one is here to handle
like updates and deletions and different
things like
that this one the index nodes you know
know the name isn't like quite clear
what it does it builds the index and the
name um and then this one you can like
always like you know you can put it in a
serverless way basically so you can only
like um scale it up if you're actually
going to need to build an
index and you know it's what I was
saying you don't want to build like the
whole index all the time so how we do it
and if you're going to do it yourself
how I recommend doing it is like you
divide your data and for us it's divided
into segments and then we build the
index directly on top of those segments
so we don't have to rebuild the index
all the time uh because otherwise it
would take
ages then for the search we do it in a
distributed way so you know you have
your different query nodes uh and then
each query node is doing the search
directly so then you have parallel par
processing then we give each of them
give the result back and then a proxy is
the one you know like doing giving you
the result to the user so then combining
the the the results back and then give
you actually the good result
result and uh that's enough yapping uh
so I've decided that I was going to do a
demo so if you seen me yesterday on my
laptop it was because I built the
demo uh so uh I talked about search at
scale um I if you've seen me in like
different meetups and stuff you know
that I usually always do demos so I'm
going to go and the Wi-Fi here is not
fabulous so hopefully it works but I'm
just going to explain you know like at
the same time hopefully I can connect to
my cluster
yes um so I'm just connecting to my
cluster for full transparency I'm
obviously not running that on my laptop
uh because I'll show you how many
vectors I have but I have 5 483 million
vectors so you know it's like it's not a
crazy amount but it's a good amount and
I can clearly not store that on my
laptop so yeah I put it on our Cloud
offering I'm not here to talk about that
so no worries but I connect to basically
M that is hosted in the
cloud
so I have my index um so it's you know
like it's built on the 483 million
vectors uh the type as you see here is
an autoindex and just to explain a bit
more what we mean by that is that it's
basically our own version of hnsw if you
go for like performance optimized or
disn as well if you want to go you know
like if you want to be like save a bit
of money and then you won't you don't
you don't care if you're like a bit
slower then we also have um support for
thisn the good part is that we have some
fancy ml uh for query parameter
recommendation so you know you don't
have to like think about um the hyper
parameters that you may have for hnsw or
discan and you know we like we take care
of that for you the data set so it's a
subset of Lon 5B uh which for the people
that are not familiar it's an open-
Source multimodal data set
and yes we load 500 million vectors from
it and it's basically like clip so you
know if you're familiar with clip it's
like um image text pairs
basically and um we have it like
directly in our in our cluster so I
don't need to like you know build it
again or anything but I'm just going to
show you so I'm only going to take a
subp part of it because again you know
like the whole data set is
gigantic uh so I'm going to load it on
my laptop I should actually have it
already otherwi it's going to take a
while but I'm just going to go for like
the first one and what I want to show
you here I'm not going to show you the
recall because I actually have no idea
of the data set that I'm using uh but I
can just show you uh QPS you know like
how many query per second can we have un
like something um that is running 500
million
vectors
approximately um and that is running
hnsw for us so I'm reading the paret
file you know there's an ID and
embeddings there's not much um else so I
can show you the embeddings if you want
and then yeah we have that we have our
embeddings I have my data
set I just built a function um to like
you know actually Benchmark the maximum
QPS that I could have so I have my I'm
going to do my search and then for my
search then I'm giving like a batch of
data and this batch you know I'm just
going to try if I should give like 100
data at the same time 100 eddings 500
100 1,000 um and then I'm just going to
play with that and basically we're going
to see how much QPS we can have given
that we have you know around 500 million
vectors so I'm just going to run that
and that's the definition of the
function and then you know it's what I
said um this one you know like would
check like I'm going to run with like
100 vectors 500
1,000 and then here is what I said
before you know it's like the different
parameters list but we abstract that
away from you so you can just have a
look now and see and yeah basically I'm
running it so we're doing it for like
you know we done it already for 100
vectors for 500 it's done and for
1,000 hopefully should be fairly fast
otherwise my demo is broken but it
should be
good um and here you know it's just like
it's just a vector search there's
nothing else um I could like do some
filtering if I wanted to um you know
very similar to what we've seen before
uh but
just because my my talk is Vector search
at scale I only do that so we can see
those are like some you know like I
didn't optimize for anything but like if
we go for 500
vectors if we're here and like some
slash parameters you know then you know
we can play with them but we can see
what's my highest here my highest is 238
KPS per second so we have uh 238 per
second running um on our on our
connection which is like 500 million
vectors
so it's not too
shady uh likely if we were to run thisn
uh we would obviously have fewer QPS and
then it would like the latency would be
higher I'm just going to show you
quickly actually have to do that going
to show you quickly as well the latency
if the Wi-Fi is
working um but the latency should be
like about like less than 50
milliseconds from what I checked
yesterday when you've seen me on my
laptop there when I was building my
demo uh so no it's here yeah so the
average is 45 milliseconds the
P99
is uh 97 sorry the P99 is 97 so about
100 the average uh was about 45 Mill
seconds so that was like you know just
an idea of how you can like then do
search at scale but not done uh have
more yapping to do so there's also like
a thing that I actually like you know
like Joe yesterday talked about Kali he
really loves it there's something that I
really love uh which is something that
is made by Nvidia so you have you know
the usual nearest neighbors H you have
the different indexes you know like Brit
Force avf whatever you have one that is
called kagra who's familiar with
kagra not
surprised so kagra
it's uh it's an algorithm developed by
Nvidia so it's basically hns W but on
gpus so it's hnsw on
steroids and it's going to like paralyze
your queries as well even for like
individual queries so then you know it
allows you to have like a higher
throughput and lower latency as well
obviously gpus are more expensive than
CPUs so then you know you might not
always use it but just going to show you
a quick Benchmark so you can have an
idea of you know what's going to happen
and I like the performance that it has
so we have like this benchmarking setups
you so it's running on AWS and then we
have two gpus um two instance types that
are running gpus and one that is running
a
CPU so just for disclaimer I'm only
trying on M like there's no comparison
with the others but it was just like to
show you just the impact of adding GPU
search you know um it's not towards like
the other Vector database but you can
see uh which only a search batch size of
one you know your hnsw on CPU is about
600 s per
second if you add um IVF Flats you know
on gpus you're about a th000 you're
already happy but you so it's not
mind-blowing you know uh if you go kagra
which is the Nvidia one um if you go on
T4 then you have about 4,000 qu per
second if you go on the A10 then you
about 500 uh 5,300 qu per second so you
can see like already the Improvement you
know like it's really a good Improvement
but also remember gpus are really good
like batch they're not very good at you
know like individual
cies um just bigger batch um so yeah
like your hnsw is about
650 uh T4 you had 12,000 here um and
then if you go on A10 you had about
20,000 C per second if the same for you
know bat size is higher I won't recite
the numbers but you can see gpus really
like when you have a batch size that is
quite big so then with this one you have
at 30 32,000
qu per second whereas on CPU you are
like I'm going to be kind I'm going to
say 700 qu per
second and then also what's cool is that
for the index building it's also way
faster so even though yes it's more
expensive in the end because it's way
faster you can also then stop you know
like your your node running the index so
for CPUs about 500 milliseconds and then
on gpus you're about about a minute or
even less
and then what's fun is that they have a
whole paper where they did um they try
to scale their indexing using kagra and
so then they have raw text which is one
terabyte of raw text which is a lot it
takes about 12 hours to inest the data
um you know they're working on like
improving it um and then they just did a
tumbling window chunking of like 300
nothing fancy it's not they don't really
care about that so you have 2.5 terab of
vectors but then the building to build
the index it takes about an
hour if you do it on CPU takes about six
days uh so yes technically gpus are more
expensive but then you know like you
would actually then save a lot of time
but you know not you don't spend six day
six days building your index also like
maybe your process will crash or
something so so yes and then just so you
have an idea so some benchmarks with
recall hnsw is blue
hsw is on the left side for the screen
uh and on the right side it's everything
that is related to kagra so you know you
can see your hnsw the recall of
0.85 we can say like 3,000 is request
per second and kagar the highest one is
at more than 10,000 again B size of one
so you know it's not where you
shine you increase the B size you go to
10 you about 100,000 uh 100 ques per
second W kagra whereas you know your
hnsw is about
[Music]
40,000 if you go for the lowest recoil
and then you know if you want to
increase your recall then uh you about
20,000 uh for hnsw and you still add
about 80,000 for the for
CRA but then gpus love big battery so if
you go for 10,000 then uh you know the
query per second you are actually don't
have the numbers but you add more than a
million um
for uh for kagra sorry whereas hnsw
would be like in around
100,000 so yeah ever do that um you can
like you know what I talked about before
but increase the number of data nodes so
then you know you have like better in
ingestion performance also you can place
the different index in quer noes on
different CPUs uh gpus sorry um and yeah
incre increase like the segments size so
then you know like the sech latency and
throughputs will also increase then it
looks like that uh so yes so for now
like you know then your query node is
running directly on gpus your index node
is running on gpus and then that's how
then you can use kagra if you want
to uh and then have like some insane uh
scale and yeah now when I took at scale
what is a scale for us um I think a
biggest uh single
instance about 10 billion vectors uh our
biggest one on communties is about 100
billion so that's usually the scale uh
we're talking about and that's it I was
Stan B I work for M thank
you fantastic thank you Stephen so yes
some big numbers there so do we have any
questions for stepen from the
floor you all understood it completely I
guess
thank you some some great numbers um
today I learned that
uh t gpus love batches but can you give
me um some just so I can wrap my head
around um how you would apply that can
you give me some use cases or some
practical use cases where you see
queries coming in in those large batches
that you can process them so I can
understand them uh for us it's it's like
it's like some really big customers you
know like you like think of governments
uh where like I'm working with one and
they have petabytes of data for example
so then it's like it's more in that one
and I think they have I remember the
numbers they have like 30 million people
living there uh and then they're
building actually a whole like rack
system and a oration system like where
everything's on an app and so then they
need like everyone is using their app to
do everything so like think you're
buying a car then they're actually
scanning the you know the app and be
like yeah I transfer the ownership to
that and then they G basically do like a
search through like everything that has
ever happened with the citizen um so
like think every email that's has been
shared with the government and
everything like that so that's that's
the kind of use case obviously I just
wanted to show it because not a lot of
people know it and I thought it was cool
uh but yeah that's the kind of use case
where it's useful not for every
day great thank you so we have I think
we had a question at the back
here hey uh n so question about the
search performance uh from the indexing
I think it's clear that gpus outperforms
the CPUs but like on search performance
I did get like what is the expected uh
Improvement there like in P for example
which one oh sorry do you see sorry May
in the see so this one uh for example is
a benchmark using gpus where you have
the recoil as well on the bottom
part and this is using IVF or you also
hsw on the left it's hnsw so running on
CPUs on the left okay like here here
you're running on CPUs on the very left
one okay and then uh yes those two are
IVF running with raft which is you know
like the rapid um algorithms from Nvidia
and then kagra which is like hsw on GPU
on the right side so
here and here is IVF on gpus
okay thank you thank you thanks and I
also noticed you seem to have your own
personal collection of Suites on your
table very impressive you know thinking
now well
done okay so um uh oh we've got a
question from our online audience um
Andy hind hi Andy uh I may have missed
if CPU GPU have compatible data on S3
can you mix and match what do you mean
do you understand the question question
um can we repeat the question I may have
and you may have to retype this but I
may have missed if CPU or GPU have
compatible data on S3 uh but I can you
mix guess if you were talking about
sorry the slides are coming on Zoom uh I
guess if we're talking about those so
here um like the gpus are talking
directly to data there last three as
well okay and then the way we do it is
that so we don't throw everything at the
GP you um if we don't want to so if you
do like a qu is like you know like I
don't know two you have two eddings and
then then we're going to do a CPU search
and then we usually redirect for GPU for
heavy
loads okay guess that can answ the
question yeah hope that answer to your
question Andy if we entirely
misinterpreted please retype it and try
again um any other questions from the
floor hello great talk thanks um I have
a question like can I run milus on my
own infrastructure on premise and do you
provide feasible infra um instructions
how to do it and then you know if
something is underperforming can I EAS
find the documentation what needs to be
scaled if it's a query now okay uh yes
yes you can running on on premise or
wherever on bed as well like we work
with arm at the moment you also like do
like very small um Vector search uh so
yes you can then there's documentation
you have to tell me if you actually find
the answers I find the answers but I
know it's a lot so uh so yes you
can to find the answers in the
documentation you need some kind of I
don't search engine I don't know yeah
it's something weird
like okay and another question online uh
de b i observed that at high recall at
around 0.95 H&S on on CPU performance
dropped significantly yes why so good
question I don't know the answer okay so
I won't I won't go live and be like try
okay okay well well maybe we'll um we'll
research that and answer it on slack yes
see if we can we we can find the answer
and come get back to you on that one but
well done I you get a badge for beating
one of our speakers
um uh and jagier uh jagier asks uh is
this ready to be deployed in the hot
path of search such as on a big
e-commerce website
yes all depends on the on the funding
you
have no so so yeah I mean we
have GPU search is very Niche so like
you know for now it's still quite
expensive so mostly wanted to talk about
it uh I wouldn't recommend it except if
you have incense scale as I talked
before you know like your government or
something um so like for an e-commerce
website um try with CPU first then if
you really struggle we can go on gpus
you know then it's only about rebuilding
the index um for like to be like GPU
ready and then it can work that way okay
thank you um okay uh any other questions
from the
floor yes I'm on the
back yeah hi nice talk sorry I could
maybe get this from documentation but
just out of the box uh are the notes in
the milw can they have multiple roles so
or
what can they have like are the notes in
milus multi-roll so single note could be
an indexer or whatever or is it uh
always split so when no it's always I
mean except if you go stand alone uh but
otherwise it's always split yeah okay
thank
you
okay that way you can like scale up in
like each one of them
individually okay any further questions
right please give a round of applause to
Steve thank you very much